The 2024 AP Physics 1 exam has a couple of
questions
that relate to oscillations, pendulums,
and
springs, so I will be going over these in
a
few videos. And even if you're not doing
AP
Physics 1, if you're doing high school
physics,
this is still really, really good
practice,
and maybe even goes beyond what you're
learning,
but it's still really, really good to
know.
So, in an experiment, the student attaches
one
end of a spring to a force sensor that is
attached
to a wall. The other end of the spring is
to a cart with a mass m equals 0.25
kilograms.
So, we know the mass, 0.25 kilograms.
The student places a motion detector to
the
right of the cart, as shown in Figure 2,
and
pulls the cart to the right a small
distance
so that the spring is stretched. And then
the
cart is released from rest, and the cart's
spring
system oscillates. And the following graph
shows
the velocity of the cart and the force
exerted
on the cart by the spring as functions of
time
t. So, before we even get started, this is
relating
to what we learned in the previous video
about
kinetic and potential energy.
These are the maximums for kinetic energy.
So, at here, kinetic energy is at max, and
all
of these points are when the cart is
either
at the farthest or at the closest to the
wall.
Or the force center. So, that's good to
know.
And this is the force. And using your data
in
the velocity-time graph, calculate the
change
in kinetic energy of the cart from t
equals
0.5 seconds to t equals 2.0 seconds.
Show your steps and calculations. This
part
a is really, really, really easy.
All you gotta do is do simple math.
Don't know how to explain that further.
It's
really self-explanatory. Delta Ke equals
Ke
final minus Ke initial.
So, one over two mv final squared
minus one over two mv initial squared.
And then you can factor this out if you
want.
One over two mvf squared minus vi squared.
And now it's just a matter of plugging in
our
values. What do we have for m? We have
0.25
kilograms times 0.25.
The final velocity, well, would be at two
seconds.
So, we just read our graph. At two
seconds,
the velocity is zero. So, it's just zero
squared.
I'm not gonna write that down. Initial
velocity
is 0.5 seconds, which is 0.3.
0.3 squared.
And when you type this into your
calculator,
you would get one over two times 0.25
times
0.3 squared. You would get 0.011
joules because it's force.
And it's negative because it's minus vi.
Now, using the data in the force-time
graph,
estimate the change in momentum of the
cart
from t equals 0.5 seconds to t equals 2.5
seconds
and briefly explain how you arrived at
your
estimation. So, if you didn't look at my
momentum video, check it out because it's
really
helpful and it relates directly to this
question.
This is a classic impulse question.
Change in momentum. The first thing when
you
see this is you want to think delta-p,
change
in momentum, is equal to impulse. So,
impulse
from time t equals 0.5 to t equals 2.5.
0.5 to 2.5. Impulse is just the measure of
the area beneath the force-time curve.
I've mentioned that in my momentum video.
So, the area here, let's call this, we
don't
actually have to calculate it, let's call
this
negative x, doesn't matter.
The area here, however, is positive x.
It's the same magnitude, but it's in a
different
direction. So, the total net impulse or
the
total net area under this part will be
zero.
So, that means the change in momentum is
And you can also use logic.
Here, here, the velocity is the same.
When you look at the graph, the velocity
is
the same, so change in momentum is zero.
So, you're obviously not going to write
that
because it asks you to use a force-time
graph,
not the velocity-time graph, but it's
still
a good thing to affirm your answer.
And what you would say is the area, the
net
area, under the force-time
graph from t equals 0.5
seconds to t equals 2.5 seconds is zero.
This means that the impulse or
the change in momentum is
also zero.
And that's basically it for this question.
Okay, three, I explained it in part two.
Basically, you say that the velocity here
is
the same as the velocity here. Momentum
depends
on mass times velocity. Mass is constant.
So, from 0.5 to 2.5, if velocity is also
the
same at 0.3, then momentum will be the
same.
So, I'm not going to write that down
because
that's going to take time, but that's
basically
it. So, these are pretty straightforward
questions,
and they basically connect momentum with
springs.
This is rotational motion. I'll get to
that
in another video. But, we have this
question.
I think that's the next one. Yep, we have
this
question, and I'm going to be going over
that
in the next video. Bye!